a final consequence of amal's law that
we will discuss is the law of
diminishing returns let's say that we
had an original processor which we will
call gen one in which our execution time
can roughly be divided into a purple
phase and a blue phase each of them
takes about half the execution time
let's say that in the generation 2
processor we decided to speed up the
blue phase by a factor of two what we
got now is that the purple part is not
affected and the blue part is now half
as long the overall speed up of the Gen
2 processor over gen 1 is equal to 1
over half is not enhanced half is sped
up by a factor of two and we get a speed
up of
133 which is a sizable speed up now
let's say that we have a generation
three processor where we again get the
blue part and speed it up by a factor of
two
relative to the Gen 2 processors now we
have that the purple part is still the
same and the blue part is half of what
it was the speed up of the Gen 3
processor over a Gen 2 processor is one
over and now we have to be careful the
unaffected part is now 2/3 of the
execution time the affected part is only
1/3 and that part is still affected by a
factor of two so the overall speed up is
1.2 over Gen 2 if we keep keep improving
the blue part over the generations
eventually we will get to almost no
speed up why because we are
improving what amounts to less and less
of the execution time furthermore
usually it is the case that improving
something initially is not very hard but
after you exhaust the easy methods for
improvement it becomes very very
difficult to get new speed UPS on a
thing that has been already enhanced
hugely So eventually the solutions
that will improve the purple part will
be cheaper than the solutions that
further improve the blue part just
because all of the easy stuff on
improving the blue part we have already
done so not only do we get lower speed
UPS by improving the blue part it's
actually becoming more difficult to do
so this is sort of a lesson to computer
Architects to not go overboard improving
the same thing because the things that
have already improved are now a smaller
percentage of the new execution time and
we need to reassess what is now the
dominant part in the execution time in
other words once you have applied one
Improvement you need to reconsider what
is now the new dominant part in the
execution time and definitely when
applying amd's law we need to consider
what is now the fraction enhanced and
the fraction unenhanced